Finding Aid for Pond Family Papers 1841-1939
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Pond Family Papers 1841-1939
Pond Family
Ann Arbor, Michigan and Chicago, Illinois family. Correspondence of Elihu B. Pond, editor of Michigan Argus, his sons, Chicago architects, Irving Kane and Allen Bartlit Pond, founders of firm of Pond & Pond, and other family members; include materials concerning family affairs, architectural projects, Jane Addams and the work of Hull House, European travels, politics especially as relates to period of the Civil War and the election of 1896; also photographs, architectural drawings and other visual materials.
852090 Aa 2
9.6 linear feet in 13 boxes
2 oversize drawers
1 microfilms
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection was donated in 1940 by the estate of Irving K. Pond (donor no. 1085 ). Some materials were donated in the same year by the American Academy of Arts and Letters (donor no. 1168 ).
The collection is open for research.
Irving Kane (1857-1939) and Allen Bartlit Pond (1858-1929) were born and educated in Ann Arbor. They were the sons of Elihu Bartlit and Mary Barlow Pond. Elihu Pond was editor and publisher of an Ann Arbor newspaper and later the warden in the state prison at Jackson. Early in their careers, the brothers moved to Chicago. Irving Pond moved there in 1879 after receiving his degree in civil engineering from the University of Michigan. He worked as a draftsman in various architectural firms. Then in 1886, he joined his brother Allen (who had recently moved to Chicago) in the practice of architecture under the firm name of Pond & Pond. Together they shared credit for many buildings including Hull House, the Chicago Commons, the City Club in Chicago. And in Ann Arbor, their buildings included the Michigan Union and the Michigan League.
By Allen's own characterization, Irving was the more creative of the two and Allen the more scholarly. Consequently, in the Chicago firm of Pond & Pond, Irving was the more productive architect, while Allen assumed most of the responsibility for the business affairs of the firm. The firm accepted jobs throughout the country and Irving often traveled to supervise construction.
Like his father Elihu, Allen Pond worked diligently for reform in public and special education. He sat on the Board of the Public Education Association and became very interested in the cause of education for the blind and the handicapped. Allen had taught Latin for three years in Ann Arbor before moving to Chicago, and it was while teaching at Chicago's Armour Mission School that he was first introduced to the young Jane Addams. Excited by her idea of establishing a settlement house in Chicago on the model of London's Toynbee Hall, he helped Addams to locate the original Hull House building and to organize the settlement. One of the first trustees of Hull House, he remained on the board for life and became a close personal friend of Miss Addams. In her speech at his funeral, which is included in the printed text of the Memorial Service for Pond, she recounted their many years' work together. Miss Addams was acquainted with the Pond family in Ann Arbor and the family letters include many references to her visits and speeches there.
Except for the original building which was the old Hull family home, all of the structures in the Hull House complex were designed by Irving and Allen Pond. Both firmly believed that the social effectiveness of the project was dependent upon the physical environment. Allen repeatedly expressed the opinion that architecture, unlike the more ephemeral arts of music, literature and theater, and the less conspicuous arts of painting and sculpture, could greatly influence the human spirit. In an essay, he suggests that architecture "offers the opportunity to aid signally in making an environment that shall contribute to the health, comfort, charm and distinction of human life". The brothers' dedication to architecture was founded upon the belief that man needs beauty if he is to prosper spiritually. Art to them was a necessary counter-influence to the growth of industry and mechanization in the city.
These architects' involvement in settlement houses was not restricted to Hull House. They also designed and were active in the management of the Chicago Commons, the Northwestern University Settlement, the Gads Hill Center and the Henry Booth House.
Through his activities with Hull House and in an attempt to further the cause of Chicago's many reform movements, Allen initiated in 1896 an attack on corruption in the city government. The Municipal Voters' League, which he founded that same year, and the Union League Club were two organizations which were useful to him in effecting social change. As an expert on labor relations, he often served as an arbitrator in Chicago's strikes and boycotts.
The distinction between the professional and non-professional aspects of the Pond brothers' careers was never very clear. With the same talents by which they earned their livings, they were able to serve the city and bring about their ambitions of social change and reform. The belief in cooperation and the power of complementary forces - artistic, social and spiritual - is a theme which runs through the writings of both and is perhaps best exemplified by their own lives together.
Summary Contents List
Allen Bartlit Pond papers [Boxes 1-3]
Irving Kane Pond papers [Boxes 3-6]
Other family members and miscellaneous
Elihu B. Pond papers [Box 6]
Louise Pond papers [Box 6]
Miscellaneous Pond materials [Box 6]
Visual materials
Photographs [Box 7]
Sketches and watercolors [Box 7]
Cased photographs [Box 8]
Albums [Box 9]
Etching plates [Box 9]
Outsize architectural drawings [Box 10 and Drawers 1 and 2]
Outsize photographs [Box 10]
Outsize sketches and watercolors [Boxes 11-13 and Drawer 2]
The Pond Family papers consist primarily of correspondence and other materials of architects, Irving Kane (1857-1939) and Allen Bartlit Pond (1858-1929) documenting family matters, European travels, their involvement in the civic and social life of Chicago, and professional activities. The collection has been divided into four subgroups: Allen B. Pond papers; Irving Kane Pond papers; papers of other family members and miscellaneous; and visual materials.
Correspondence comprises the bulk of both the Allen and Irving Pond subgroups. This correspondence consists almost exclusively of exchanges between the brothers when they were separated because of travel, and with their parents and sister. There is little correspondence with clients, professional associates, or others outside of the family. The letters, however, are often detailed and revealing of the thoughts and activities of the Pond brothers. In addition to the usual descriptions of landscapes and social events when traveling abroad, their letters contain many comparisons of European and American trends in architecture, housing, the development of cities. To their family and with each other, the brothers also wrote of their non-professional interests: Chicago politics, social settlements in the city, humanitarian causes, and their involvement with various literary groups. Of note in the Allen Pond papers are letters containing references to Jane Addams and her work at Hull House. There are also accounts they received from family about Jane Addams and her talks when visiting Ann Arbor. Letters concerning Jane Addams are dated Sept. 1896; Jan. 1898; Sept. 18, 1898; Jan. 22,1900; Mar. 1901; May 28,1901; June 15,1901; undated 1901; Apr. 21,1902; July 7,1902; Aug. 18,1902; Feb. 16, 1903; Jan. 12,1904; Jan. 23,1905; Feb. 1905; May 29,1907; Mar. 1908; and Apr. 1908.
Their sister, Mary Louise and their mother, Mary Barlow (Allen) Pond wrote weekly of family affairs and the social and cultural events of Ann Arbor. Both comment extensively on the ideas and activities of many of the leading intellectual and literary figures of the day - William James, John Dewey, Kipling, Wharton and Shaw - as well as on their daily interactions with Angells, Cooleys and other prominent Ann Arbor families. Unfortunately, there are few surviving letters from Allen and Irving to the family in Ann Arbor. Much of the information in the collection about their work is therefore by indirect reference only.
Subjects:
Pond, Allen Bartlit, 1858-1929.; Pond, Elihu Bartlit, 1826-1898.; Pond, Irving K. (Irving Kane), 1857-1939.; Addams, Jane, 1860-1935.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Architects--Illinois--Chicago.; Architecture--Illinois--Chicago.; Chicago (Ill.); Europe--Description and travel.; Illinois--Politics and government--1865-1950.; Michigan argus.; Michigan--Politics and government--1837-1950.; Michigan--Politics and government--1861-1865.; Michigan--Politics and government--1877-1898.; Presidents--United States--Election--1896.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Micigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Football.; Voyages and travels.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Architecture.; Cadillac (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; California.; Chicago (Ill.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Construction industry.; Detroit (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Detroit Opera House (Detroit, Mich.); East Lansing (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Harbor Point (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Hill Auditorium (University of Michigan); Hotels and taverns.; Illinois.; Interiors--Hotels and taverns.; Interiors--Theaters.; Italy.; Lansing (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Mason (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Michigan League.; Michigan State University--Buildings.; Michigan Union.; Northwood Hotel (Cadillac, Mich.); Pond, Allen Bartlit, 1858-1929.; Pond, Ashley, 1827-1910.; Pond, Elihu Bartlit, 1826-1898.; Pond, Irving K. (Irving Kane), 1857-1939.; Pond, Mary Barlow Allen, 1826-1915.; Saint Joseph (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Student Publications Building (University of Michigan); Taft, Lorado, 1860-1936.; Theaters--United States.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; Whitcomb Hotel (Saint Joseph, Mich.); World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.)
Contributors:
Pond, Allen Bartlit, 1858-1929.; Pond, Elihu Bartlit, 1826-1898.; Pond, Irving K. (Irving Kane), 1857-1939.
Genre/Form:
Albums.; Ambrotypes.; Architectural drawings.; Caricatures.; Daguerreotypes.; Diaries.; Drawings.; Paintings.; Photographs.; Prints.
- Allen Bartlit Pond
  The Allen Bartlit Pond subgroup is divided into Biographical Material, Correspondence and Writings. The correspondence is primarily with is brother Irving and other family members. The writings include some poetry and articles and essays on architecture and a variety of social issues. While in Europe, Allen Pond conducted several studies of European settlement houses from which he prepared a number of the articles and essays. These writings are included in the folder Notes and Manuscripts re: Settlement Houses.
  - Biographical materials
    - Text of Memorial Service for Allen B. Pond (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Undated, 1881-December 1895, 35 folders (Box 1)
    - January 1896-December 1907, 43 folders (Box 2)
    - January 1908-1914, 15 folders (Box 3)
    - 1926-1927, 1937 (Box 3)
      (letter received after his death)
  - Writings
    - Poetry (Box 3)
    - "Architecture and Religious Life" (Box 3)
      Manuscript copy
    - "James Russell Lowell"-Paper presented to the Chicago Congregational Club, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Notes and Manuscripts re: Social Settlements (Box 3)
    - Manuscripts re: Employer-Employee relations (Box 3)
    - Juvenile writings pre-1880, 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts
      - 1886-1890 (Box 3)
      - 1912-1923 (Box 3)
      - Undated (Box 3)
    - Scrapbook of published articles by Allen B. Pond 1880s-1890s (Box 3)
      (includes unsigned articles, perhaps of Irving K. Pond)
- Irving Kane Pond
  The Irving Kane Pond subgroup is comprised of three series: Biographical materials, Correspondence and Writings and Miscellaneous.
  - Biographical materials
    The Biographical materials series contains one folder of personal and family information and one reel of microfilm of a draft manuscript autobiography probably written in the 1920s. The manuscript of about 300 pages provides information about Pond's youth in Ann Arbor; his experiences at the University of Michigan, including scoring the first touchdown for the varsity football team in 1879; and information about various architectural projects and social causes in which he and his brother were involved.
    - Miscellaneous information (Box 3)
    - Autobiography of Irving Kane Pond, 1 microfilms positive and negative copies (Reel 1)
      [Original located at the American Academy of Arts and Letters. Not to be quoted, reproduced, or published without permission.]
  - Correspondence
    - Undated, 1876-December 1882, 12 folders (Box 4)
    - January 1883-December 1893, 37 folders (Box 4)
    - January 1894-December 1939, 41 folders (Box 5)
  - Writings and miscellaneous
    Although Irving Pond was involved with settlement houses and reforms, his interests carried him more deeply into the artistic and literary circles of Chicago. A more prolific writer than Allen, he contributed regularly to the Chicago Literary Club, published several books. He often lectured on art and architecture, and he documented his travels and his career with numerous sketches and watercolors. Irving never lost his childhood fascination with the circus, and in 1937 he published his book Big Top Rhythms on this subject. He was himself an accomplished gymnast, and he saw gymnastics as an art equal to any of the more traditional forms of artistic expression. This series includes most of his extant writings.
    - Certificates (Box 6)
    - Musical Compositions (Box 6)
    - Poetry (Box 6)
    - Speeches, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Big Top Rhythms, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - "History of the Class of '79: University of Michigan" (Box 6)
    - Manuscripts Submitted to the Chicago Literary Club, 4 folders (Box 6)
    - Articles and Reviews re: Art and Architecture (Box 6)
    - Manuscripts re: Puritans (Box 6)
    - Notes and Drafts (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts circa 1874-1879, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts undated (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
- Other family members and miscellaneous
  The subgroup titled Other Family members and Miscellaneous contains correspondence and other material by Elihu and Louise Pond and a short history of the architectural firm of Pond & Pond and a listing of the major works by the Pond brothers.
  - Elihu Pond
    Included in the family papers is a small amount of the correspondence and writing of Elihu B. Pond, father of Allen and Irving. A journalist by profession, his letters offer many observations and opinions on politics, economics and the affairs of the University of Michigan. The 1896 Presidential campaign and the issue of Free Silver were discussed in particular depth and the letters often contain specific comment on the implications of current events for Chicago business and politics.
    Elihu served as warden of the Jackson State Prison from 1883 to 1885, and on the Ann Arbor Board of Education for many years. He discussed the problems encountered in these activities in his editorials for the Michigan Argus and the American Peloponnesus. His journals from 1864, 1865, 1867 and 1898 offer explicit accounts of the weather, but little of substance concerning his work or his times.
    - Manuscripts for the American Peloponnesus, 1847-1850 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous manuscripts (Box 6)
    - Journals 1864, 1865, 1867, 1898, 4 volumes (Box 6)
    - Scrapbook containing editorials written by Elihu B. Pond for the Argus (Box 6)
  - Louise Pond
    - Poetry (Box 6)
    - Compositions (Box 6)
    - Composition Fragments (Box 6)
    - Autograph book (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Miscellaneous family correspondence 1866-1910 (Box 6)
    - Pond & Pond Architectural Firm: Historical background and list of works (Box 6)
- Visual materials
  The Visual Materials subgroup contains photographs, sketches, watercolors, and architectural drawings of Irving Kane Pond, his brother Allen Bartlit Pond, and their architectural firm, Pond & Pond. It includes materials relating to architectural commissions, especially in Chicago and Chicago suburbs and at the University of Michigan; also travel sketches and paintings of Irving Kane Pond from Italy and California. The photographs, including some daguerreotypes and ambrotypes, are images of buildings designed by the Pond brothers, individual and family photos, photos of the family of Lorado Taft and drawings of collaborations between Pond and Taft.
  - Photographs
    - Architectural subjects
      - Illinois
        - Chicago
          - Baptist Home Missionary Training School for Women 1908 (Box 7)
          - Chicago Telephone Building 1904 [construction] (Box 7)
          - F.I. Carpenter House, Woodlawn Avenue (Box 10)
          - LaSalle Street Factory (Box 7)
          - McCormick House, Buena Avenue 1890s (Box 7)
          - McCormick House, Buena Avenue (Box 10)
          - Pullman Building 1883 (Box 7)
          - Ravenswood Church 1915 (Box 7)
          - Tulane Building? (Box 7)
        - Evanston. C.M. Howe House (Box 7)
        - Oregon
          - Public Library 1907 (Box 7)
          - Soldiers' Memorial (Box 7)
        - Park Ridge Public Library (Box 7)
        - Pullman. Pullman Lake (Box 7)
        - Rock Island
          - Royal Neighbors of America National Headquarters 1928 (Box 7)
      - Indiana
        - West Lafayette
          - Purdue University Memorial Union (Box 7)
      - Kansas
        - Lawrence
          - Kansas University Memorial Union 1926 (Box 7)
      - Michigan
        - Ann Arbor
          - Michigan League
            - Construction (Box 7)
            - Exteriors (Box 7)
            - Interiors (Box 7)
            - Paintings by J.E. McBurney (Box 7)
          - Michigan Union
            - Construction (Box 7)
            - Exteriors and interiors (Box 7)
        - Cadillac
          - Northwood Hotel (Box 10)
        - Harbor Point
          - Dummer Cottage (Box 7)
        - Lansing
          - Mutual Building 1928 (Box 7)
        - Mason
          - Mason Public School (Box 7)
        - St. Joseph
          - Whitcomb Hotel 1927 (Box 7)
          - Whitcomb Hotel (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Sturges Crematorium (Box 10)
        - Unidentified (Box 10)
      - Nebraska
        - Omaha
          - War Memorial 1925 (Box 10)
      - New York
        - Wyoming
          - Fire Station 1900 (Box 7)
          - The Hall 1900 (Box 7)
      - Washington
        - Seattle
          - Washington With the Sword of State, statue (Box 7)
      - Washington, D.C
        - Department of State Building proposal (Box 7)
      - Wisconsin
        - Kenosha
          - First National Bank (Box 7)
      - Unidentified
        - Buildings
          - Construction (Box 7)
          - Exteriors, 2 folders (Box 7)
          - Interiors (Box 7)
        - Unidentified ornaments (Box 7)
        - Unidentified sculpture (Box 7)
        - Unidentified theater (Box 7)
    - Personal subjects
      - Allen B. Pond (Box 7)
      - Ashley Pond (Box 7)
      - Elihu B. Pond (Box 7)
      - Irving K. Pond (Box 7)
      - Mary Barlow Allan Pond (Mrs. Elihu B. Pond) (Box 7)
      - Groups (Box 7)
      - Homes (Box 7)
      - Individuals, Identified, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Individuals, Unidentified, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - Oregon, Illinois, with family of Lorado Taft (Box 7)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
      - Various (Box 10)
  - Sketches and watercolors
    - Architectural subjects
      - China
        - Shanghai
          - United States Building, Burlingame Ward Memorial 1914 (Box 11)
            (also includes adaptations for Buenos Aires and Rio de Janeiro)
      - Illinois
        - Chicago
          - Chicago Woman's Club 1921 (Box 7)
          - Chicago Woman's Club (Box 11)
          - Churches (Box 11)
          - David Swing Settlement Buildings (Box 11)
          - Hull House and Chapel at Ewing Street (Box 11)
          - Hull House Coffee House (Box 7)
          - L.Z. Leiter Building (Box 11)
          - North American Building (Box 11)
          - North American Building (Box 7)
          - North American Building 1910 (Map-case 2)
          - Residences and offices (Box 11)
          - South Shore Congregational Church (Box 7)
        - Des Plaines
          - Congregational Church 1927 (Box 11)
        - Evanston
          - Judge Eliot Anthony Residence (Box 11)
        - Highland Park
          - Highland Park Club House (Box 11)
          - Highland Park Club House (Box 7)
        - Kankakee
          - Federal Building 1904-1906 (Box 11)
        - Lake Forest
          - Gymnasium (Box 11)
        - LaSalle
          - Hegeler House (Box 11)
        - Oak Park
          - Paul Blatchford Squash Court, etc (Box 7)
        - Oregon
          - Artists' Colony (Box 7)
          - Public Library (Box 7)
          - Public Library (Box 11)
        - Park Ridge
          - Public Library (Box 11)
        - Riverside
          - Langford Residence (Box 7)
        - Sycamore
          - Gymnasium and Music Hall 1901 (Box 11)
      - Indiana
        - Culver
          - Culver Military Academy Memorial Gate 1922 (Box 11)
        - West Lafayette
          - Purdue University Memorial Union 1921 (Box 11)
      - Massachusetts
        - Wellesley
          - Student-Alumnae Building proposal (Box 11)
      - Michigan
        - Ann Arbor
          - Michigan League (Box 7)
          - Michigan League 1927-1928 (Box 12)
          - Michigan Union 1910 (Box 12)
          - School of Religion proposal 1923 (Box 12)
          - School of Music proposal 1929 (Box 12)
        - Detroit
          - Detroit Opera House 1887, 1933 (Box 12)
          - Ashley Pond Stable (Box 12)
        - East Lansing
          - MAC Union Memorial Building 1922 (Box 12)
        - St. Joseph
          - Whitcomb Hotel 1926 (Box 12)
      - Missouri
        - Kansas City
          - Kansas City Exchange Building proposal 1886 (Box 13)
      - New Brunswick
        - St. John
          - General Public Hospital 1928 (Box 13)
      - New York
        - Wyoming
          - Clock Tower 1902 (Box 13)
          - The Hall 1900 (Box 13)
          - The Hall (Box 7)
      - Washington, D.C
        - Roosevelt Memorial proposal (Box 7)
      - Washington
        - Seattle
          - Washington With the Sword of State, statue 1906 (Box 13)
      - Illustrations for The Meaning of Architecture (Box 13)
      - Unidentified
        - Churches (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 13)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
    - Student work (Box 13)
    - Portraits and caricatures (Box 7)
      (also in oversize box 13)
    - Travel
      - Illinois (Box 7)
      - Italy (Box 7)
      - Michigan (Box 7)
      - Unidentified landscapes and buildings (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Cased photographs
    - Daguerreotypes
      - Unidentified man writing, broken binding, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 1]
      - Man with hair standing up, broken binding, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 2]
      - "Elia" (penciled on binding), young man writing with scroll in hand, 1 clasp, broken binding, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 3]
      - "Stephen Allen" (penciled on binding), good condition, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 4]
      - Woman with lace gloves and bonnet, poor condition, no case, unsealed, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 5]
      - "Jared---" (penciled on binding), man with blue shirt, out of case, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 6]
      - Man with long neck, out of case, 3"x3.5" (Box 8)
        [no. 7]